Guide to the International Monitor Institute. Rwanda Videotapes and Audiotapes, 1992-1999 RL.00607
David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library
- Rwanda Audiotapes Series (Audiocassette), 1993-1994, 8 boxes
  - RTLM 66, Sony Super EF 90 (Box 126, Audio-cassette RW040)
    Kantano commence la face A. Il salue les efforts de la radio "soeur," Radio Rwanda. Il se moque ensuite des Inkotanyi qui ont des barbes et chevelure hirsute et plein de poux. Il dit que les Iinkotanyi "sont foncièrement méchant." Kantano s'adresse ensuite aux "dépouilles" de Hutu qu'il offre comme preuve du but exterminatrice des Inkotanyi qu'il accuse d'avoir traumatisé des enfants et bébés. Il exhorte la population de se lever pour combattre les "Inyenzi" et il ajoute que le Rwanda exterminera les "Inyenzi" qui sont d'ailleurs "suicidaires." Kantano passe ensuite à une attaque contre Museveni qu'il accuse de vouloir régner sur toute l'Afrique centrale. Il termine son monologue avec une référence aux Tutsi de Burundi qui sont en train de créer des problèmes pour ce pays. Ananie prend la relève et donne les informations. Il note l'arrivé des Français et il fait mention de la création d'un Tribunal international pour le Rwanda. Il ajoute que la RTLM est parmi les accusés. Gahigi prend la suite et défend les actions de la RTLM. Il essaie de démontrer que la RTLM n'est pas à l'origine des problèmes entre les "Inyenzi" et le Rwanda. Il dénonce ensuite Dallaire et René Denis Ségui qu'il accuse d'avoir fabriqué de faux rapports pour convaincre la communauté internationale de la méchanceté de la RTLM. Kantano termine la cassette avec plusieurs déclarations que les "Inyenzi" et même les Tutsi sont décimés.
  - RTLM 67, Sony Super EF 90 (Box 120, Audio-cassette RW041)
    Air Date: 1994 Jul. 03
    Kantano et Ananie sont les animateurs de cette cassette. Les thèmes de cette cassette sont, parmi autres: (1) Museveni en tant que chef des "Inyenzi" et son objectif de créer des petits pays Tutsi, (2) l'intervention Française et la création d'une zone de sécurité pour empêcher les Inkotanyi de continuer leurs massacres, (3) preuves de "régions dépouillées par les Inkotanyi" et l'idée que des "adventuriers Tutsi cherchent tout ce qui est Hutu," (4) des attaques contre René Denis Ségui et les radios étrangères qui font de faux reportages contre les Hutu et indiquant la prise de la ville de Kigali, (5) des atrocités commis par les Inkotanyi qui tuent même les bébés, (6) la promesse que les Inkotanyi seront exterminés et même une référence aux "Tutsi décimés."
  - RTLM 68, Sony HF 60 (Box 120, Audio-cassette RW042)
    This tape contains some evidence of general incitement. Towards the end of side B, the last sentence of the second to last paragraph, a reference to 10 Germans who have disappeared should probably be double-checked.
    This tape contains a long discussion by Bemeriki about the creation of a new parliament in Gisenyi and the role of the PSR (Rwandan Socialist Party). Ruggiu focuses on foreign journalists' misrepresentation of the situation in Rwanda. He also reports on the "military situation" in some detail.
  - RTLM 69, Sony Super EF 90 (Box 120, Audio-cassette RW043)
    Air Date: 1994 Jul. 3
  - RTLM, Sony HF 60 (Box 120, Audio-cassette RW044)
    Air Date: 1994 Jan. 1
  - RTLM, Sony HF 60 (Box 120, Audio-cassette RW045)
    Air Date: 1994 Jan. 05-06
    Much of side B is inaudible -- The tape is fairly light and humorous in tone. Kantano pokes fun at most of the Rwandan Patriotic Front (RPF) leadership with stereotypical comments about Tutsis.
    The tape contains Kantano's account of his visit with the RPF at the CND. He lists a series of RPF dignitaries alternately poking fun at them and accusing them of wanting to obtain power. It also contains an interview with Deputy Rutaremara of the RPF. Kantano casts the interview as an example of the Inkotanyi way of thinking.
  - RTLM, Sony Super EF 90 (Box 120, Audio-cassette RW046)
    Air Date: 1994 Jan. 6
  - RTLM 147, Sony Super EF 90 (Box 120, Audio-cassette RW047)
  - Problème régional, Kiga-Nouga, Sony Super EF 90 (Box 120, Audio-cassette RW048)
  - Mesindik (Sindikubwabo at Butare), Sony Super EF 90 (Box 120, Audio-cassette RW049)
    Unidentified Kinyarwanda news caster begins with news headlines: (1) Prime Minister Kambanda's meets with religious, political, and party leaders in Gitarama, (2) UN Special Representative Booh-Booh's pledges "never to forsake Rwanda," (3) 400 Belgian troops are leaving Rwanda.
    Reporter Rwakana Gaspard continues with report on Kambanda meeting which allegedly discussed ways of ensuring the security of displaced people. These measures include appointing and replacing prefects and appointing a new Army chief of staff. These measures are allegedly hindered by the Rwandan Patriotic Front (RPF)'s unwillingness to stop fighting.
    Rwakana then reports on the RPF's "unlucky streak" and the FAR's control over all the communes in Ruhengeri save Butaro. Rwanaka repeats that despite the government's best efforts, security of refugees can only be ensured if the RPF stops fighting. Bourgmesters present at the meetings also blamed the shortcomings in security on logistical problems and a shortage of policeman, vehicles, and fuel.
    Unidentified newscaster continues with (1) report on the FAR's control of Nkumba and Kidaho communes in Ruhengeri, (2) UN support for cease-fire, (3) announcement of Western Europe Foreign Affairs Ministers' decision to send food aid and the departure of 400 Belgian troops.
    Unidentified French newscaster repeats the headlines and the report on Kamabanda meeting.
    Reporter Hyacinthe Bicamumpaka repeats earlier reports on Kambanda meeting adding (1) that it was intended to "persuade the population to cease their vindictive acts and the settling of scores" and (2) to dismiss prefects who were unsuccessful at controlling violence. Bicamumpaka then repeats the remainder of the headlines, this time further specifying FAR strongholds on Byumba, Mutara, and Kigali.
    An unidentified Kinyarwanda reporter continues with report that officials have set up several meetings to "clear up misunderstanding among the population" and to help re-integrate people who have fled. This message was reportedly delivered by Sindikubwabo in Gikongoro, in Maraba commune, Butare, and in Nyakizy, Butare. The Gikongoro Prefet gave the President three reasons for the breakdown in security: (1) anger over Habyarimana assassination, (2) a belief that given the opportunity, the RPF would "not spare them at all," (3) simple banditry. The President reportedly answered that revenge does not justify violence.
    A taped version of Sindikubwabo's speech follows. In the speech the President (1) urges Rwandan's to watch over each other like gendarmes and not repeat the story of Cain and Abel, (2) argues that gendarmes, population, and army have complementary roles,(3) insists that "security" is primarily the citizens' responsibility, (4) says that citizens who think themselves above the government's orders should be identified and punished.
    Sindikubwabo continues alleging the enemies strongest weapon is his ability to sow ethnic division. This division causes Rwandans to seek magic cures for their problems rather than finding and questioning those who support the enemies' allegations. "That's how the enemy fulfills this plan without using... bullets... those who do not understand are requested to listen before its too late."
    Reporter breaks in adding that the President asks refugees to return to their property wherever possible.
    Sindikubwabo tape continues with President urging for the closing of camps and for people to master their anger despite the dying of people and the destruction of houses.
    Musabirema take the microphone again and says that the President aired his concern about the refugees in Cyahinda Parish who have guns and grenades and killed and wounded 7 people, including the burgomaster. The President also reportedly requested the suppression of unauthorized patrols and roadblocks.
    Side A ends with Musabirema summarizing the main points of Sindikubwabo's speech in French.
    Likely date: April 5, 1994; likely transmission identity: Radio Rwanda (see Annex 5 Les Medias de Genocide)
    Tape features report on Kambanda's meeting with leaders in Gitarama and excerpts from Sinkibubwabo's speech in Gikongoro. The broadcast's overt message is that the government is trying to protect refugees, but the calls for everyone to participate in ensuring their fellow citizen's "security" are ambivalent.
  - Discours de Léon, Sony Super EF 90 (Box 120, Audio-cassette RW050)
    Cette cassette contient le discours de Léon Mugesera qui existe déjà: voir Archive Box #053
    Ruggiu est le seul animateur de cette cassette. Il donne les informations politiques de la journée. Il rapporte aussi l'infiltration des "Inyenzi" dans Kigali et ses alentours. Il vise en particulier les "Inyenzi" de Kacyiru et de Nyamirambo. Ruggiu passe ensuite à un interview avec Gérard Karanganwa, le burgomaster de Kicukiro. Karanganwa rapporte que les Inkotanyi ont commis des atrocités dans sa commune et celle de Gikondo au point qu'il n'y a plus d'habitants à Kicukiro. Ruggiu lui souhaite "bon travail" et termine la cassette en notant qu'il est inconcevable que les Inkotanyi gouvernent le pays même si ils gagnent la guerre.
  - RTLM Début, Sony HF 60 (Box 120, Audio-cassette RW051)
    La grande partie de la face A contient des chansons de Anonciata Kamariza qui n'ont pas été traduite
    Il n'y a pas de date pour cette cassette
    Un journaliste non-identifié commence la face A en visant trois soi-disant Inkotanyi: Sentama Abdallah, Iyakaremye et Nyilimpunga. Il accuse aussi la Rdio Muhabura d'avoir diffusé des rumeurs fausses. La face B consiste entièrement d'un interview entre Gahigi et Ferdinand Nahimana. Les thèmes de cette interview sont: (1) l'évolution du FPR qui trouve ses origines chez les "Inyenzi" de 1959, (2) le caractère "Ugandais" du "FPR-Inyenzi," (3) le phénomène Kanyarengwe, un Hutu qui a combattu les "Inyenzi," et son "différend" avec le Président Habyarimana, ainsi que son "élimination" imminente du FPR et la crétion de deaux factions FPR, l'une Hutu, l'autre Tutsi, (4) le FPR en tant que organisation qui pratique l'extermination de ses opposants depuis le temps de Rwabugiri et qui continue cette même pratique de nos jours dans la zone tampon (5) la notion que le FPR-Inyenzi refuse de partager le pouvoir et qu'il s'attaque à tout le Rwanda et pas seulement au MRND.
  - Interhamwe, Sony Super EF 90 (Box 120, Audio-cassette RW052)
    This tape consists of an interview of Janvier Afrika one of the original leaders of the Interahamwe. Major Mutambuka leads Afrika through a detailed account of the Interahamwe's inception and its first three missions. Afrika reveals the names of men who were instrumental in first forming the Interahamwe, then providing it with the necessary support to carry out its missions and protect its members. Afrika also explains how he helped start the newspaper "Umurava" and the extent to which President Habyarimana was involved.
  - Loose Tape, Mugesera, Leon MRND, Sony Super EF 90 (Box 120, Audio-cassette RW053)
    Air Date: 1992 Nov. 22
    There is very strong evidence in this speech including specific calls to "eliminate" and "kill" Tutsis and members of opposition political parties.
    This is a tape of Leon Mugesera's speech at a political rally in November of 1992. The theme of the tape is the "invasion" of Rwanda. Twagiramungu and Uwilingiyimana are specifically targeted as leaders of this "invasion." The general purpose of the speech is to warn the audience of this threat and suggest that appropriate action be taken, including separating or sending away any participants or supporters of the "invasion."
  - A/900, Sony HF 60 (Box 120, Audio-cassette RW054)
    Air Date: 1994 Apr. 2
    *Special Note: Date of cassette may be incorrect. According to additional transcript sources located at The Montreal Institute for Genocide and Human Rights Studies (MIGS), the broadcast references the death of the President Juvénal Habyarimana. Original broadcast date must therefore be post April 6th, 1994, the date of Habyarimana's death.
  - A/901, Sony HF 60 (Box 120, Audio-cassette RW055)
    Air Date: 1994 Apr. 5
  - A/902, Sony HF 60 (Box 120, Audio-cassette RW056)
  - A-903, Sony HF 60 (Box 120, Audio-cassette RW057)
    Air Date: 1994 Apr. 07
    There is little evidence of incitement to genocide but numerous references to "maintainig security" and establishing cooperation between the population and the FAR. There are also several references to raids and setting curfews.
    This tape is from the day after Habyarimana's assassination. It consists mostly of instructions to the population in the form of communiqués from the FAR and various prefects. It also includes a short speech by President Sindikubwabo. The broadcast has a tone of no nonsense efficiency as plans are outlined for establishing "security" throughout the country.
  - A/904, Sony HF 60 (Box 120, Audio-cassette RW058)
    Air Date: 1994 Apr. 09
    Un journaliste non-identifié, Bemeriki et Ruggiu commence cette cassette en expliquant que l'assassinat de Habyarimana a donné suite à des incidents de violence dans le pays. Ils expliquent que le nouveau Président, Monsieur Théodore Sindikubwabo, a été choisi selon l'article 42 de la Constitution Rwandaise car les Accords d'Arusha n'avaient pas encore été mis en place. L'émission passe ensuite aux cérémonies du nouveau gouvernement auxquelles les Ministres prêtent serment. Sindikubwabo continue la cérémonie avec un discours au cours duquel il annonce leplan d'installer un comité de crise pour veiller sur et régler les problèmes de sécurité. Bemeriki suit le Président Sindikubwabo. De son côté elle loue la vigilance des Forces Armées Rwandaises et de l'Interahamwe de sorte que les Inkotanyi ont très peu de complices parmi la population de Kigali. Bemeriki déclare aussi que le FPR a l'intention de semer le désordre et que les Inkotanyi ont déjà tué Kanyarengwe, un Hutu.
  - A/905, Sony HF 60 (Box 120, Audio-cassette RW059)
    Air Date: 1994 Apr.10
    Un ou deux journalistes non-identifiés, Jean-François Nsengiyumva et Jean Baptiste Bamwanga sont les animateurs de cette cassette. Elle contient aussi un discours du Premier Ministre Jean Kambanda, un interview avec le Colonel B.E.M. Gatsinzi et d'un interview entre Bamwanga et Karamira, Karemera et Ngirumpatse. Les thèmes de cette cassette tourne tous autour de l'assassinat du Président Habyarimana, le nouveau gouvernement, la sécurité, la violence dans les rues, l'installation de comités de sécurité et d'une auto-défense. A plusieurs reprises des membres du gouvernement demandent à la population de suivre les directives des comités de sécurité dans leurs quartiers pour ce qui concerne l'installation des barrière. Les trois politiciens offrent des explications pour la violence à Kigali. Ils expliquent que la mort de Habyarimana a rendu la population furieuse. Ils demandent à la population d'établir la sécurité etde cesser la violence mais isl demandent aussi de redoubler de vigilance.
  - A/909, Sony HF 60 (Box 120, Audio-cassette RW063)
  - A/910, Sony HF 60 (Box 120, Audio-cassette RW064)
    Air Date: 1994 Apr. 13
    Producer: RTLM and Radio Rwanda
    Cette émission est animé par des journalistes de Radio Rwanda aussi bien que de la RTLM. La première partie de la cassette est animé par un journaliste non-identifié, Hyacinthe Bicamumpaka et Jean Baptiste Murutampunzi tous originaire de la Radio Rwanda. Cette première partie s'adresse surtout aux événements des derniers jours qui ont produit de nombreuses "victimes innocentes." Ces journalistes, à l'aide de communiqués officiels, demandent à la population de retrouver le calme tout en restant vigilant. Parmi d'autres, les Belges et la MINUAR sont dénoncés d'avoir aidé le FPR qui est dénoncé à son tour d'avoir repris les hostilités. Par contre, la communauté internationale est louée pour avoir condamné les actions du FPR. Jean Kamband a suit ces premiers journalistes avec un discours qui explique que "les moments difficiles" qui caractérisent le Rwanda sont le résultat de la peine et fureur de la population à cause d ela mort de leur Président Habyarimana. Lui aussi dénonce le FPR ainsi que Twagiramungu. Il ajoute que la population doit rester calme toute en doublant de vigilance. Bemeriki passe au micro ensuite et accuse les Belges d'avoir assassiné Habyarimana tout en accusant la MINUAR de négligence. Bemeriki est suivit d'un entretien entre Ruggiu et Thomas Kabonake, un journaliste avec "L'Echo des Mille Collines." Les deux hommes insistent que le FPR préparait cette guerre depuis six mois et qu'ils essaient maintenant de s'infiltrer parmi la population histoire de les confondre ainsi que les soldats du FAR. Kabonake ajoute que le FPR aurait payé certaines agences de presse étrangères pour qu'elles publient de fausses informations. Kantano prend la suite et lance une attaque contre Shyaka de la Radio Muhabura. Il ajoute que la RFI, la BBC et la RTDF sont tous coupables d'avoir diffusé de faux reportages. Il conclut son monologue avec des incitations à la population de rester courageux et vigilant. Un journaliste non-identifié suit avec des nouvelles des combats à Kigali. Nsengiyumva prend la relève et s'entretient avec Froduald Karamira de la MDR. Celui-ci se contente de dire qu'ils sont fiers du comportement de la population tout en dénoncant les actions des Inkotanyi. La cassette se termine avec Kantano qui déclare que les Rwandais sont en train de gagner la guerre déclenchée par les Inkotanyi. Il traîte les Inkotanyi de "maigrichons" et dit qu'ils étaient "animés" par l'orgueil au début de la guerre.
  - A/912, Sony HF 60 (Box 120, Audio-cassette RW066)
    Air Date: 1994 Apr. 14-15
    Cette cassette commence avec un entretien entre Bamwanga et Niyitegeka, Ministre de l'Information. Niyitegeka maintient que les Inkotanyi sont pourchassés parout dans la ville de Kigali. Un journaliste non-identifié intervient pour annoncer les résultats d'une réunion concernant la sécurité de Kigali: la population doit se mettre à défendre sa propre sécurité, des patrouilles nocturnes seront de rigeur dorénavant... L'entretien de Niyitegeka continue. Celui-ci déclare que: (1) la Belgique est impliquée dans les attaques du FPR, (2) la population doit veiller contre l'infiltration des Inkotanyi, (3) le FPR n'a aucune raison de ne pas reconnaître le nouveau gouvernement Rwandais. Karamira suit l'interview avec un monologue qui rapporte sur les événements de Kigali. Il avertit le FPR que les rumeurs propagées par les Inkotanyi risque de faire massacrer tous les Tutsi. Kabendera passe au micro ensuite pour lire le journal national. Il annonce que: (1) des blancs se trouvent parmi les forces du FPR, (2) les Inkotanyi ont l'usage de l'équipement Ugandais, (3) les Inkotanyi ont commis de nombreuses atrocités à Kigali, mais ils se font quand même pourchassés par les forces Rwandaises. Venuste Bahiyize prend le micro et continue les même thèmes. Il ajoute que le FPR essaie d'introduire des complications pour éviter les négociations. La cassette se termine avec l'interview d'un soldat Inkotanyi par le Major Gérard Ntamagezo de la FAR. L'entretien révèle que les Inkotanyi sont coupables d'avoir tué des membres du CDR. Le soldat ajoute que de son avis le deux partis (le FPR et le gouvernement Rwandais) devraient cesser la guerre et prendre leurs places à la table de négociations.
  - A/913, Sony HF 60 (Box 120, Audio-cassette RW067)
    Air Date: 1994 Apr. 15
  - A/914, Sony Super EF 90 (Box 120, Audio-cassette RW068)
    La face B est vierge
    Cette cassette est entièrement composée d'une discussion entre Bamwanga, Mugenzi, Ndungutse, Karemera et Hyacinthe Nsengiyumva. Parmi autres, ils s'adressent aux thèmes suivant: (1) la collaboration de l'ancien Premier Ministre Uwilingiyimana avec les Inkotanyi, (2) les "Inyenzi" sont la minorité et ne peuvent jamais espérer gouverner le pays, ils ne peuvent que tenter de détruire le Rwanda, (3) un avertissement que le FPR tentera "d'exterminer la masse," (4) les Accords d'Arusha ne sont plus valables, (5) les Inkotanyi refusent de reconnaître le gouvernement Rwandais parce qu'ils préfèrent exterminer la population, (6) la population doit collaborer avec le gouvernement et essayer de re-établir la sécurité, (7) il faut laisser la population achever le travail de la révolution de 1959.
  - AV/915, Sony HF 60 (Box 120, Audio-cassette RW069)
  - AV/916, Sony Super EF 90 (Box 120, Audio-cassette RW070)
    The first part of the broadcast consists of a Gahigi interview of Shyirambere Barahinyura who blames Tutsis for the rise of ethnic tensions. He goes on to explain that the Inkotanyi are not Rwandans and have enlisted the help of both the Ugandans and Belgians in their war effort. Barahinyura then launches into a tirade against the new government accusing them of maintaining a harmful silence in the face of the Inkotanyi's attacks which will result in the extermination of Rwandans. Gahigi follows the interview with a short monologue accusing the Inkotanyi of committing a number of atrocities.
  - AV/917, Sony Super EF 90 (Box 120, Audio-cassette RW071)
    Air Date: 1994 Apr. 16
    Side A of the tape begins mid-sentence. Journalist Hyacinthe Bicamumpaka (1) reports on the Defense Minister's praise of the population's "bravery" and patriotism in helping the army, (2) suggest that the Rwandan Patriotic Front (RPF) is receiving logistical and material assistance, such as helicopters, from foreign countries, (3) claims that in the north and in Kigali the RPF is now "infiltrating to reach places that it could not conquer by arms.. ."
    Bicamumpaka continues with a summary on the various options under discussion by the UN Security Council.
    After a break in the tape, Bicamumpaka praises the "courage" of the Rwandan people following the "assassination of the Chief of our State by criminals." The Reporter then introduces his interviewee, Eliezer Niyitegeka, Minister of Information.
    Niyitegeka explains (1) that cell leaders who "finish their duty" receive rewards from the government, (2) that cell leaders are in a position to "ensure security" by organizing the population to "conduct patrols" and "fight against and denounce the enemy to the authorities." Niyitegeka also (3) stresses that the government has always needed the cell leaders in this capacity.
    Niyitegeka continues by saying (1) that the Rwandan army is fighting against the "enemy," (2) that the "enemy" violates the population's rights by shooting at innocent people and burning them alive in their houses, (3) that the population should continue fighting alongside the soldiers and in their place against the "small Inkotanyi," and (4) that the population should do this with whatever weapons it has—spears, bows, and arrows.
    Following Bicamumpaka's mention of "Inkotanyi wickedness," Niyitegeka (1) suggests that 3,400 of the RPF's 4,000 soldiers in Kigali are either infiltrators or spies, (2) asserts that in Gikondo and Nyabarongo, Inkotanyi have killed innocent people, (3) and that Inkotanyi trained by RPF soldiers encircle civilian families at night and throw grenades at them.
    In response to a question about Muhabura and Bujumbura Radio, Niyitegeka denies the "enemy's" claims regarding refugees and the fleeing of top government ministers.